Brookfield, Ill. First Congregational Church records, 1894-2013.
Congregational Library & Archives
Brookfield, Ill. First Congregational Church records, 1894-2013.
RG5583
Congregational Library & Archives
2.58 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
The First Congregational Church of Brookfield, Illinois, was formally gathered on November 25th, 1894. Construction on the church building was completed in 1897. The building underwent renovations in 1907, 1919, 1938, and again in 1947. The church was expanded in 1955 to support the Sunday school and create community focused spaces. The church joined with the United Church of Christ in the early 1960s. The church dissolved in 2013; the church building continues to function as a church today. This collection contains records related to the administration and membership of the First Congregational Church. The collection also contains records from auxiliary groups, especially from the Women's Fellowship, as well as contains membership records, including membership lists and directories, and vital records.
First Congregational Church (Brookfield, Ill.)
First Congregational Church (Grossdale, Ill.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in December 2024; accession number 2024-46.
Custodial History
Materials in this collection were given to the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ, likely at the time of the church's closing. There is no further documentation on how the materials arrived at the Illinois Conference.
Historical Note
The village of Grossdale, Illinois, was first settled in 1889 with the sale of lots by real estate investor Samuel Eberly Gross. The First Congregational Church was formally gathered on November 25th, 1894. Rev. J. C. Meyers became the first minister of the church in 1895; he was quickly proceeded by Rev. George H. Grannis in 1896. That same year, plans for the construction of a church building were put into motion. Construction on the church building began in March, 1897, and the dedication service for the new building was held a few months later on May 23. The village of Grossdale changed its name to Brookfield in 1905. The church building, with support from congregations in La Grange, Western Springs, and Hinsdale, underwent significant repair work in 1907 to fix the building's foundation and heating plant.
During World War I, the Men's Club presented speakers on topics related to the war effort. In 1919, the church underwent renovations to once again repair the furnace; the effort was supported by "Furnace Parties" which raised part of the cost of the renovation. A plan to merge with the Methodists in Brookfield was considered around 1920 but ultimately did not come to pass. In 1922, the church purchased a house adjacent to the church building to be used as a parsonage. Additional plots of land were purchased in 1927 to support a significant expansion of the church's facilities but this expansion never came to pass.
In 1938, the church building underwent some remodeling to support the purchase of a pipe organ in hopes that the organ music would refresh and improve worship services. Following the purchase and installation of the organ, the church underwent additional renovations to raise the church, create a recreational center, and redecorate both the interior and exterior of the church. 1938 also saw the formation of the church's Friendship Club. In 1943, the Ladies Aid Society and the Amafeurasia, a missionary group, merged to form the church's Women's Fellowship. During World War II, the church's Social Action Committee published a the "Bits o' News" newsletter which facilitated connections between the parish and those from the church serving during the war.
Another significant renovation took place in 1947, this time with the purpose of making the building "the most useful and architecturally beautiful building in Brookfield." This once again saw the building's exterior redone and the interior refurbished. The plan to expand the church was revisited again in 1955 with a proposal to build a new parsonage, remove the old parsonage, and build a new wing of the church dedicated to the Sunday School which was facing significant crowding issues. Unlike the 1927 plan, these expansions came to fruition.
The church continued to serve the Brookfield community in the decades after. It joined the United Church of Christ in the early 1960s. The church dissolved in 2013 with its final service held on May 19th. The Women's Fellowship continued to exist alongside the church until the church's dissolution. The church building was sold and continues to function as a church today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to the administration and membership of the First Congregational Church in Brookfield, Illinois. The majority of the records are administrative in nature and include meeting minutes for the church council and trustees. The collection also contains records from auxiliary groups, especially from the Women's Fellowship (also called the Dorcas Chapter), and committees of the church, such as the building renovation committee and the social action committee. The collection also contains a small amount of records related to the activities of the church's Sunday school. The collection also contains membership records, including membership lists and directories, and vital records such as baptismal records, marriage records, and necrologies.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged into the three topical series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged into chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1894-2013
Series 2: Committee and auxiliary group records, 1894-1993
Series 3: Membership records, 1940-2012
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Scrapbooks.; Soldiers -- United States -- Correspondence.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Brookfield (Ill.) -- Church history.; First Congregational Church (Brookfield, Ill.); First Congregational Church (Grossdale, Ill.); Grossdale (Ill.) -- Church history.
- Administrative records, 1894 2013; 1894-2013
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administrative functions of the church. This series includes meeting minutes for the church council and trustees, financial records, constitutions, and other church records.
  - Minute book, 1894 1907; 1894-1907 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Minute book, 1907 1914; 1907-1914 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Miscellaneous financial records and correspondence, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minute book, 1915 1923; 1915-1923 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Miscellaneous church and membership records, 1919 1922; 1919-1922 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1923 1943; 1923-1943 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Minute book, 1944 1957; 1944-1957 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1945 1958; 1945-1958 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Trustee records, 1954 1959; 1954-1959 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Miscellaneous church records, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1958 1965; 1958-1965 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Constitutions, 1959 1965; 1959, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trustee records, 1960 1969; 1960-1969 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Church records, 1961 1965; 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1966 1969; 1966-1969 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1970 1974; 1970-1974 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1974 1975; 1974-1975 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1975 1978; 1975-1978 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1978 1982; 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1982 1985; 1982-1985 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1985 1989; 1985-1989 (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1989 1991; 1989-1991 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Council meeting minutes and records, 2004 2007; 2004-2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Council meeting minutes and records, 2011 2013; 2011-2013 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Committee and auxiliary group records, 1894 1993; 1894-1993
  This series contains records from both auxiliary groups and committees of the church. The series includes women's fellowship records, a social action committee scrapbook related to soldiers in World War II, meeting minutes for the building renovation committee, and records from the church's Sunday school.
  - History of the women's fellowship, 1894 1945; 1894-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - History of the women's fellowship, 1894 1972; 1894-1972 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Friendship club records, 1938 1946; 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sunday school records, 1939 1945; 1939-1945 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Social action committee World War II scrapbook, 1942 1944; 1942-1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Social action committee World War II loose materials, 1943 1945; 1943-1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Sunday school records, 1945 1946; 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Congregational players scrapbook, 1948, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Stewardship and benevolence committee records, 1958 1988; 1958-1988 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Women's fellowship records, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Women's fellowship events and newsletters, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women's fellowship constitution and by-laws, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dorcas chapter records, 1968 1993; 1968-1993 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Women's fellowship yearbook, 1969 1971; 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Building renovation committee records, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Membership records, 1940 2012; 1940-2012
  This series contains records related to the membership of the church. The series includes yearbooks and directories, baptismal records, marriage records, transfer records, membership lists, and necrologies.
  - Yearbook and directory, 1940 1980; 1940, 1969-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Church membership, 1953 2012; 1953-2012 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Marriage records, 1988 2005; 1988-2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Transfers and dismissions, 1992 2011; 1992-2011 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Baptismal records, 1993 2012; 1993-2012 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - New members, 1994 2009; 1994-2009 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Necrologies, 1995 2011; 1995-2011 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - In memoriams, 1997 2012; 1997-2012 (Box 2, Folder 20)